A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Colonel William Preston Papers, 1774-1789
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Colonel William Preston Papers, 1774-1789
The Library of Virginia
APA 223
.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
Virginia. Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (Misc. Reel 655).
Biographical Information
Colonel William Preston (1729-1783) was born in Limavady, Ireland, to Colonel John Preston and his wife Elizabeth Patton. The family immigrated to Augusta County, Virginia, in 1738. He served in the House of Burgesses from Augusta County from 1766 to 1768, and in 1769 served as a burgess from the newly formed Botetourt County. Preston married Susanna Smith on 17 January 1761 and together they had 12 children. The family lived at Smithfield Plantation in Blacksburg, Virginia.
During the Revolution he was elected to the Committee of Safety for Fincastle County and was also responsible for military affairs in Montgomery County and the rest of southwestern Virginia. Colonel Preston was vital in preventing uprisings by the British loyalists in southwest Virginia. The General Assembly, during its session begun in October 1782, passed an act granting William Preston and others immunity from any prosecutions resulting from their suppressions of a Loyalist uprising in 1780.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1774-1789, including letters, orders, and statements of Col. William Preston, relating to the defense of southwestern Virginia from the British loyalists and Indian allies of the British during the American Revolution. The bulk of the collection are letters detailing various aspects of the Revolutionary War. Topics include rumors of attacks in Botetourt and Montgomery Counties, Virginia; the Battle of Kings Mountain, S.C.; Lord Cornwallis' movements towards Virginia; the Battle of Camden, NJ; and requests for troops from Montgomery County, Va. Correspondents include Col. Martin Armstrong, Col. Arthur Campbell, General William Campbell, Col. William Christian, Col. Elijah Clarke, Ben Cook, Walter Crockett, William Davies, Dudley Diggs, Col. William Fleming, Governor Benjamin Harrison V, Governor Thomas Jefferson, Col. Charles Lewis, Patrick Lockhart, General Lachlan McIntosh, James McGavock, James Montgomery, Governor Thomas Nelson, Jr., General Andrew Perkins, Mayor Thomas Quirk, and Col. George Skillern, among others.
Included are several noteworthy letters: Letter, 30 October 1778, from General Lachlan McIntosh at Fort McIntosh, Beaver, Pa., to Col. Preston, regarding General McIntosh's efforts to secure peace treaties with Native American tribes and a request for troops from Virginia. Letter, 25 November 1778, from Col. Preston to Governor Patrick Henry detailing General McIntosh's letter and Col. Preston's difficulties in securing men to send to General McIntosh's aid. Letter, 7 April 1779, from Walter Crockett, warning Col. Preston of British plans to destroy lead mines and cause destruction in Montgomery County, Va. Letter, 15 April 1779, from James McGavock to Col. Preston naming soldiers who were accused of being Loyalists, listing their units and punishments. Also included is a deposition, 18 April 1779, by Michael Hennigan, an informer who told of the British plans to destroy lead mines and cause destruction in Montgomery County, Virginia.
Also of note are several letters detailing interactions with Native Americans loyal to the British, especially the Cherokee Nation. Included is an extract of Col. Elijah Clarke's letter, 1780, detailing attacks on the old and infirm after a battle in Georgia. Letters, 10 and 15 April 1780, from Martin Armstrong, Surry County, North Carolina, to Walter Crockett, warning of an upcoming attack by the Cherokee Nation along the frontiers from Georgia to Virginia. Letter, 7 June 1780, containing intel about Native Americans on the way to the Fort at Falls of Ohio (near Louisville, KY) and asking for military support. A deposition, 11 December 1780, of William Springstone, formerly a trader in the Cherokee town of Citico (Monroe County, TN), about the Raven chief of Cherokee, a treaty with a British agent in Georgia, a planned attack on the inhabitants of Virginia, and an attack around Chilhowee (Cherokee town in Blount and Monroe Counties, TN).
Additionally of note is a letter, 3 July 1780, about the defeat of the British at the Battle of Ramsour's Mill, Lincolnton, NC. An account, 10 October 1780, of the Battle of Kings Mountain, SC, and the death of British Major Patrick Ferguson. Letter, 15 February 1781, from Governor Thomas Jefferson to Col. Preston, regarding Lord Cornwallis movement towards Virginia's boundary and asking Col. Preston to get troops together to send to Gen. Nathanael Greene. Letter, 12 June 1781, from Col. William Fleming to Col. Wm Preston, about the critical situation with Lord Cornwallis, discussing the raid at Charlottesville by Lord Tarlton, and mentioning General Friedrich von Steuben's help in Virginia. Also included are the proceedings, 2 July 1782, of field officers of the militia of Montgomery and Washington Counties, Va., with a plan for the defense of the frontier. Included is a petition, undated, from the residents of Clynch River in Montgomery County, Virginia, as to why they didn't march on the late expedition against the British army in North Carolina due to attacks by Native Americans and fears for their families and homes. Also included is a letter, undated, from Col. Preston thanking the inhabitants of town of Salem, North Carolina, for their hospitable manner towards the militia of Montgomery County, Virginia. Also is an interesting letter, undated, from Col. Preston, to "Friends and Neighbors," about several rumors and complaints he's had lobbied at him and his hopes for a more peaceful relationship with his neighbors.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Letter, Lord Dunmore to Col. Charles Lewis, 1774 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Capt. Buchanan, 1777 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter, to Governor Patrick Henry, 1778 January [7?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letter, Col. William Fleming to Col. William Preston, 1778 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter, Unidentified, 1778 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter, Gen. Lachlan McIntosh to Col. William Preston, 1778 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Governor Patrick Henry, 1778 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter, Gen. Zach. McIntosh to Col. William Preston, 1778 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- List of those who signed Oath of Allegiance, 1778-1779 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter, Ben. Cook to Col. William Preston, 1779 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter, Dudley Diggs to Col. William Preston, 1779 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Order to Col. William Preston, 1779 March (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter, Walter Crockett to Col. William Preston, 1779 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter, James McGavock to Col. William Preston, 1779 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Deposition of Michael Henninger, 1779 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter, William Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1779 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter, Walter Crockettt to Col. William Preston, 1779 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letter, James McGavock to Col. William Preston, 1779 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letter, James Montgomery to Col. William Preston, 1779 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letter, William Campbell to Col. William Preston, including deposition of Captain James Cox, 1779 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to William Campbell, 1779 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letter, Governor Thomas Jefferson to Col. William Preston, 1779 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letter, Governor Thomas Jefferson to Col. William Preston, 1779 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Letter, Governor Thomas Jefferson to Col. William Preston, 1779 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letter, Extract of letter from Col. Elijah Clarke, ca. 1780 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Letter, Col. Martin Armstrong to Walter Crockett, 1780 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Letter, Walter Crockett to Col. William Preston, 1780 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Proceedings of Officers in Botetourt County, 1780 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter, Col. Arthur Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1780 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Letter, Col. Arthur Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1780 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Letter, Mayor Thomas Quirk to Col. William Preston, 1780 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Letter, Walter Crockett to Col. William Preston, 1780 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letter, J. Breckenridge to Col. William Preston, 1780 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Letter, James McGavock to Col. William Preston, 1780 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Letter, Col. Arthur Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1780 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Letter, Jos. Martin to Col. William Preston, 1780 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Peter Kinder's Confession on the Torys (Col. Lynches Memorandum), 1780 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Letter, William Christian to Col. William Preston, 1780 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Enlistment statement, 1780 October (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Letter, Walter Crockett to Col. William Preston, 1780 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Letter, Robert Fristoe to Col. William Preston, 1780 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Account of Battle of Kings Mountain (S.C.), 1780 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Letter, Col. George Skillern to Col. William Preston, 1780 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Letter, Col. Patrick Lockhart to Col. William Preston, 1780 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- William Springstone's deposition, 1780 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Letter, William Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1780 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Letter, Col. George Skillern to Col. William Preston, 1780 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 45a)
- Extract of Letter, Col. Campbell to Major G. Christian, 1780 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Proposal for raising troops, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Governor Thomas Jefferson, 1781 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Letter, M. Armstrong to Col. William Preston, 1781 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Letter, Governor Thomas Jefferson to Col. William Preston, 1781 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Letter, General Andrew Perkins, 1781 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Letter, General Andrew Perkins to Col. William Preston, 1781 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Letter, Governor Thomas Jefferson to Commanding officer of Montgomery County Militia, 1781 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Letter, Walter Crockett to Col. William Preston, 1781 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Letter, William Fleming to Col. William Preston, 1781 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Letter, Unknown to [Col. William Preston?], 1781 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to [Col. William Preston?], 1781 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to [Col. William Preston?], 1781 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Letter, Governor Thomas Nelson, Jr., to [Col. William Preston?], 1781 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to [Col. William Preston?], 1781 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to [Col. William Preston?], 1781 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- War Office order containing note from Col. William Davies to Col. William Preston, 1781 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Blank militia returns, 1781 October (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Col. Crockett and Col. Ingles, 1782 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Governor Benjamin Harrison V, 1782 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to Col. William Preston, 1782 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Letter, War office to Col. William Preston, 1782 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Letter, Sampson Mathews to Col. William Preston, 1782 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to Montgomery County Lieutenant, 1782 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Letter, Col. William Davies to Col. William Preston, 1782 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Letter, Arthur Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1782 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Proceedings of the Officers at Ft. Chiswell (Va.), 1782 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Instructions to Col. Crockett, 1782 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Letter, William Davies to Col. William Preston, 1782 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Field Officers, 1782 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Circular with note from William Davies, 1782 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Letter, Walter Crockett to Col. William Preston, 1782 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Col. William Preston order for tax collection, 1782 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Letter, John Ward to Col. William Preston, 1782 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Letter, William Campbell to Col. William Preston, 1782 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- Letter, George Peary to Col. William Preston, 1782 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Col. William Davies and Governor Benjamin Harrison V, 1782 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 82)
- List of sums paid by collectors for the bounty of soldiers, 1782 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- Letter, James Moore to Col. William Preston, 1783 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Letter, James Bryan to Col. William Preston, 1783 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Letter, Governor Benjamin Harrison V to Montgomery County Lieutenant, 1783 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 86)
- Pay claims, 1789 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 87)
- Instructions to scouts sent to Col. William Preston, Undated (Box 1, Folder 88)
- Petition to Col. William Preston from the Inhabitants of Clynch River, Montgomery County, Va., Undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
- Proposal to raise troops from Augusta, Rockbridge, Botetourt, Montgomery, and Washington Counties, Va., Undated (Box 1, Folder 90)
- Letter, Col. William Preston to Gentlemen and Neighbours, Undated (Box 1, Folder 91)
- List of delinquent tax payers from Capt. Flower Swift to Col. William Preston, Undated (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Robert King statement, Undated (Box 1, Folder 93)
- John Henderson's confession, Undated (Box 1, Folder 94)
- Col. William Preston note of thanks to town of Salem, N.C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 95)
- Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 96)